#### MICHELLE ANDERSON-DRAPER

#### **OVERVIEW**

Michelle has been involved in education, evaluation and leadership roles for over 20 years. One of the first to receive the professional designation of "credentialed evaluator" in 2011, Michelle is adept at applying varying evaluation methodologies to meet the needs of a situation, as evidenced by her evaluation experience. Michelle works collaboratively when designing, developing, delivering and evaluating continuous improvement, learning strategies, programs and services. She brings a strong understanding of curriculum and instructional design, systems thinking and strategic planning as well as excellent communication, presentation, facilitation and consulting skills to her work. As a community and education advocate, Michelle serves on the Board of Trustees for Edmonton Public Schools.

# PROFESSIONAL DESIGNATIONS

#### Credentialed Evaluator

Canadian Evaluation Society 2011

#### **Interim Teaching Certification**

Alberta Education 2014

#### **TESOL Teacher Training Certification**

Teaching English to Speakers of Other Languages (TESOL) 2017

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# AndersonDraper Consulting Inc. Principal Evaluator Edmonton, Alberta

Focusing on initiatives that aim to improve program outcomes for children, youth, adults families, and communities. Michelle is adept at applying varying evaluation methodologies to meet the needs of a situation, as evidenced by her evaluation experience. Her skills have ensured research and evaluation findings contribute to providing strategic recommendations. Below are a some examples of projects.

### Edmonton Community Adult Learning Association (2019) Undertaking a needs assessment under the lens of an asset/or

Undertaking a needs assessment under the lens of an asset/community building approach. Multiple modes of data collection (focus/workgroup sessions, surveys, data & document review) are being used. Demonstrates a strong knowledge of adult learning principles.

#### • Indigenous Relations and Culture & Tourism (2018-2019)

Worked with Ed Marchack Consulting on the evaluations of the Indigenous Climate Change, Alberta Aboriginal Economic Partnerships Program and the Aboriginal Business Investment Fund as well as the Community Facility Enhancement Program and Enhanced Capacity Advancement Program under Culture & Tourism. Shows systems level thinking.

#### County of Strathcona (2019)

Working with Yardstick Research to complete a Youth Needs Assessment – Public Engagement.

#### • City of Edmonton (2017-2018)

Conducted 8 logic model workshops with service areas and 2 strategy sessions for City of Edmonton Leadership Team. Demonstrates understanding of City's

goals, priorities and key business areas. Completed the implementation evaluation of the Ride Transit Program.

# Community Initiatives Against Family Violence (2016-2019) Facilitated strategic planning sessions, created evaluation plan, undertook evaluation, presented findings to membership.

#### PolicyWise for Children & Families (2012-2018)

Was the co-evaluator for the Youth Community Support Program. Created the evaluation framework, logic model & undertook the program evaluation. Evaluator for Common Approach Framework: Working Together for the Delivery of Programming and Services to Pre-school Children with Disabilities (PUF/FSCD); facilitated logic model development. Year 5 Evaluation of the Government of Alberta's FASD 10 Year Strategic Plan: Outcomes review of training and networking. Brought strong project management skills.

#### • Alberta Mentoring Partnership (2014-present)

Developmental Evaluator for Children and Youth in Care and Mentoring Evaluation: includes Calgary, Edmonton and Red Deer sites. Works closely with the Advisory Committee. Designed the program guide. Brings a focus on learning, development, collaboration and partnership.

#### Boys and Girls Clubs Big Brothers Big Sisters of Edmonton and Area (2015-2018)

Evaluator for Mentoring Supports in Satellite Communities. Evaluator for the Queer Youth Mentoring Program, in conjunction with the Pride Centre of Edmonton.

#### North East Alberta Information Hub (2015-2017)

Evaluator for the Employment First Customized Employment Program funded by Alberta Supports. Created the evaluation framework, logic model & plan, and undertook the program evaluation.

#### • Terra Centre for Pregnant and Parenting Teens (2000-present)

Evaluator for the Family Wellness program. Program Review, creation of outcome measurement framework, agency theory of change & logic model workshops for each program area. Evaluator for Post High School Completion Program, Peers Educating Peers and Mental Health Supports. Babies, Books and More Evaluation. Created Mental Health Supports Evaluation Framework. Developed and programmed the Terra Talk Back Survey.

#### Alberta Children & Youth Services (2008-2011) Manager, Strategic Evaluation Edmonton, Alberta

Responsible for leading and coordinating priority Ministry and cross-Ministry evaluation projects. Provided direction, coaching and support to staff and interns. Co-chaired the Government of Alberta's Evaluation and Assessment Network.

## Canadian Evaluation Society: Alberta/NWT Chapter (2004, 2012) Instructor Edmonton, Alberta

Co-Facilitated Modules 1-4 in 2004 & 2006, 2011 & 2012.

#### University of Alberta (2004-2007) Instructor Edmonton, Alberta

Facilitator (winter 2007) Interdisciplinary 410 Program Planning and Evaluation course (HECOL 301) – Sessional Instructor (fall 2005), Co-Instructor (fall 2004), Lead Lab

Instructor (2003 - 2006) Communication: Theory and Practice (AFHE 304) – Professor (winter 2006), Lab Instructor(winter 2004).

#### LEADERSHIP & SERVICE

#### Edmonton Public School Board Trustee Edmonton, Alberta

Elected in 2013 and acclaimed in 2017, Michelle represents Ward B (Northeast Edmonton) on the Board of Trustees of the Edmonton Public School Board, where she has served as Vice-Chair (2016-17), and as Board Chair (2017-19). The Edmonton Public School Board is responsible for the education of over 105,000 students in the city of Edmonton. Their mandate is to ensure that students receive the best education possible in Edmonton's more than 213 public schools.

#### **Rotary Club of Edmonton Northeast (2017-present)**

Corporate Member

#### **Canadian Evaluation Society (2008-2011)**

National Council Representative & Case Competition Coach / Judge

#### **Teachers Training Project (2014-2017)**

Travelled to China, as invited by the Jiangsu Provincial Department of Education, through China Connections for the "Teachers Training Project", to help Chinese teachers of English improve their language skills by teaching a prepared curriculum. Jiangsu, China.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### University of Western Ontario – Commencing in September 2019

EdD Education - Professional online program - Community Leadership

#### Concordia University of Edmonton - 2013

Bachelor of Education After Degree (Honours)

#### University of Alberta - 2007

Master of Science (Honours) Family Ecology & Practice

#### University of Ottawa - 1994

Master of Arts (Honours) Health Sciences

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

# Influential Mentoring Practices for Navigating Challenges and Optimizing Learning During an Evaluation Internship Experience.

Canadian Journal of Program Evaluation 31(3), 374-396. Poth, C., Anderson-Draper, M., & El Hassar, B. (2017).

Understanding cultural competence through evaluating "Breaking the silence: A project to generate critical knowledge about family violence within immigrant communities.

The Canadian Journal of Program Evaluation, 21(2). Anderson-Draper, M. Edmonton, Alberta (2006).

# Review of Evaluation Strategies for Communicating and Reporting, Enhancing Learning in Organizations (2nd Ed.)

Thousand Oaks: CA. Sage. Canadian Journal of Program Evaluation, 21(1),185-187. Anderson-Draper, M., Book Review: Torres, R. T., Preskill, H. & Piontek, M. E., (2005).